<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Jimi Oke</title>
    <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Jimi Oke</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing hybrid buses in the near term leads to faster transit decarbonization</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-harnessing-hybrid-buses/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-harnessing-hybrid-buses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maps are good but are simpler maps better? Insights on urban bicycling in the US</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-abdalazeem-maps-are-good/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-abdalazeem-maps-are-good/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Of 684 urban counties in the United States, only 307 (45%) have publicly available bicycle maps online. From these maps, we observed five features: Level of Infrastructure, Amenity Locations, Level of Stress, Transit Locations, and Interactive features. Using these binary data, we clustered the counties via a Bernoulli mixture model to obtain a typology of three map types. The Minimal type largely features level of stress information, which indicates route difficulty or cycling comfort. The Moderate type mainly features level of infrastructure. Finally, the Complete type features the aforementioned indicators in addition to displaying the locations of transit stops and amenities. Using socioeconomic and mode share predictors from the American Community Survey for the 684 counties, along with map-related features, we fitted three XGBoost models to predict bicycle mode share. Our models indicate that map availability has a positive impact of bicycle use. Second, Complete maps are associated with lower bicycle usage, while the reverse is true for Minimal maps. Finally, of the 5 map features identified, Level of Infrastructure and Transit Locations are the most relevant in predicting bicycle usage but they have a negative association. These findings may indicate that simpler maps are more effective or that comprehensive maps may not be as effective as thought in increasing bicycling. Overall, this work lays a foundation for future planning and analyses for better bicycle maps.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust forecasting framework for energy-informed planning in urban rail transit systems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-han-robust-forecasting-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-han-robust-forecasting-framework/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi‑scale road network feature analysis in highly congested cities: Implications for sustainable cities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-kumar-multiscale-road-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-kumar-multiscale-road-network/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspectives on Accelerating Integrated Seabed Characterization for the Clean Energy Transition: Outcomes of a National Science Foundation Workshop</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-westgate-perspectives-accelerating-integrated/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-westgate-perspectives-accelerating-integrated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Global offshore wind development is rapidly expanding, with lease areas exceeding 400 square kilometers, leading to technical, economic, and environmental challenges in seabed characterization. Revolutionizing seabed characterization through integrated, cross-disciplinary scientific approaches presents an opportunity to reshape the offshore energy industry’s data requirements, collection, interpretation, and integration processes. Significant opportunities for transformative innovation lie in the development of more intelligent site characterization methods that incorporate data science-informed decision-making. The NSF-funded workshop Advancing Integrated Seabed Characterization for Clean Energy Transition (ASCENT) was held in November 2024, bringing together a geographically diverse group of international stakeholders, including academics, offshore wind developers, consultants, contractors, and government regulators. The workshop aimed to promote transformative, cross-disciplinary innovation in integrated seabed characterization methods. It focused on improving the quantification of geodata uncertainty and enhancing ground model reliability. Keynote presentations, panel discussions, and breakout sessions provided insights into regulatory perspectives on project data requirements, challenged the current state of practice in data collection and interpretation, and advanced the state-of-the-art in data integration and data science applications. This paper presents the workshop’s motivation, key outcomes, and future opportunities identified to reduce the carbon footprint and the economic and environmental costs of offshore renewable energy development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typology of U.S. transit systems reveals energy data gap and potential for diesel-based emissions reductions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-typology-us-transit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-typology-us-transit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a typology of 2,205 U.S. transit systems, derived from 167 operational indicators in the National Transit Database (NTD), to reveal distinct patterns. Using kernel principal component analysis and Gaussian mixture modeling, we identify five distinct transit system types: &lt;em&gt;Metro Bus-Rail&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mid-Sized Urban&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hybrid Multimodal&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Urban Specialized&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Diverse Operations&lt;/em&gt;. We also discover a gap in diesel consumption reporting (76% of systems), which are predominantly of the &lt;em&gt;Mid-Sized Urban&lt;/em&gt; type. To bridge this critical data gap, we apply extreme gradient boosting (XGBoost) to predict the diesel consumption for 1,674 underreported systems. We then estimate lifecycle emissions, accounting for regional grid carbon intensity. The result highlights significant variability in diesel consumption and emissions across transit types, with &lt;em&gt;Metro Bus-Rail&lt;/em&gt; systems contributing the highest emissions. To evaluate decarbonization potential, we simulate fleet electrification and grid decarbonization. Our scenario analyses indicate that up to 79% of 8.17 MMTCO&lt;del&gt;2&lt;/del&gt;e diesel-based transit emissions can be eliminated through fleet electrification, with further grid decarbonization eliminating the remainder. These findings provide actionable insights for policymakers to prioritize electrification, optimize resource allocation, and support sustainable transit strategies in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roadway Crash Typology of Census Tracts Enables Targeted Interventions via Interpretable Machine Learning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-abdalazeem-roadway-crash-typology/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-abdalazeem-roadway-crash-typology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Roadway crashes are a leading cause of death and injury worldwide, necessitating targeted interventions for improved safety. While models exist to analyze spatial variations in specific risk factor effects, a comprehensive approach to identifying and characterizing distinct types of crash-prone spatial environments across large regions remains less explored. We address this gap by introducing a novel data-driven typology of census tracts based on crash indicators across Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Vermont using 2023 crash data, providing a framework for categorizing areas based on distinct crash patterns. We apply dimensionality reduction using Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection (UMAP) to 25 crash characteristics derived from over 222,000 crash records and aggregated across 2,660 census tracts. This reveals six key latent dimensions that capture underlying variations in crash profiles. Gaussian Mixture Modeling (GMM) reveals five distinct crash types, driven by differences in speed conditions, roadway design, and vehicle involvement, which influence crash severity and frequency. We validate the typology using a Light Gradient Boosting Machines (LightGBM) classifier, which achieved 96% accuracy across 5 classes. Finally, we demonstrate how this typology enables targeted and evidence-based safety interventions. This integrated pipeline offers a novel tool for understanding regional safety patterns and guiding the development of context-specific, proactive safety interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typology of US metropolitan areas illuminates per-capita mobile greenhouse gas emissions impacts and informs mitigation strategies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-zhao-typology-us-metropolitan/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-zhao-typology-us-metropolitan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a novel typology of 349 metropolitan statistical areas in the United States and demonstrate its implication for understanding and mitigating per-capita mobile greenhouse gas emissions (PMGEs). Via factor analysis of 55 indicators across seven categories, we identified eight key drivers of mobile emissions. Based on these, we clustered the metro areas via Gaussian mixture modeling to obtain seven metro types. We used an extreme gradient boosting regression model to predict PMGEs based on all the indicators, excluding population. Using SHapley Additive exPlanations values, we identified the most relevant indicators. The model reveals that density and transit mitigate PMGEs, while car use and climate exacerbate it. The typology provides further insights into how these effects vary across network, mode share and development patterns. Ultimately, the typology can serve as a framework to identify relevant indicators and thereby guide the selection of strategies for effective, type-specific emissions mitigation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scenario discovery yields robust multi-level pathways for regional decarbonization planning</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-zhao-scenario-discovery-yields/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-zhao-scenario-discovery-yields/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a comprehensive accounting and scenario discovery framework for sector-specific regional greenhouse gas emissions. Three regions in Connecticut, namely Bridgeport, Hartford, and New Haven, served as case studies. Our inventory approach combines bottom-up and top-down approaches, relying on readily available data sources. We also fitted autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) models to project near-term emissions across all sectors in each region. The models indicate that absent any interventions, current emissions trends will remain unchanged. Sensitivity analysis highlights the importance of truck mileage and grid emissions factors in emissions. Critically, we then apply the data-driven scenario discovery method to elicit nine robust decarbonization pathways at the mild, moderate and deep level. Our results show that deep decarbonization is attainable but requires a concerted multi-sector approach focused on mobility, grid emissions, commercial emissions and residential fossil fuel use. We expect that this framework will be easily deployable to other regions, serving as a useful tool to identify key areas of focus for equitable and effective emissions mitigation planning efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distilling actionable insights through road network features to alleviate traffic congestion</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-kumar-distilling-actionable-insights/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-kumar-distilling-actionable-insights/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Policy transfer is an efficient strategy for urban policymaking. However, the unique city-specific characteristics complicate the transfer of congestion-mitigating policies. We study seven highly congested cities worldwide and argue that, since regions with less congestion exist even within these cities, understanding how road network features explain the intra-city variations in con- gestion can significantly enhance the efficacy of mitigation measures. While our findings reveal extreme city-specific variations in feature importance, suggesting that supply-side interventions must be tailored to individual cities, the most effective features for demand-side interventions share notable similarities across different cities. In the short term, our results directly impact the ongoing mitigation measures in these cities, such as congestion pricing and personalised route choice applications, specifically in making them more robust and increasing public acceptance. In the long term, our insights encourage a re-evaluation of scepticism towards infrastructure invest- ments in mitigating congestion and highlight the potential for designing congestion-resistant future cities. Moreover, given the diverse selection of cities, the few common observations suggest that extrapolating those common observations to new cities will likely be effective, especially when a detailed analysis like ours is impossible due to data constraints. Finally, we provide key recommendations for researchers from the data-driven traffic prediction community regarding the need to focus on microscopic scales and for researchers in simulation-based counterfactual approaches to simulate the impact of road network features with values beyond the known ranges for feature values in the studied cities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel typology of fatal crash behaviors via natural language processing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-han-novel-typology-fatal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-han-novel-typology-fatal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study presents a data-driven framework to uncover patterns of less-studied fatal driver behaviors. We analyzed 84,170 driver behavior reports from the Fatality Analysis Reporting System (FARS) between 2021 and 2023.  Using natural language processing methods, we obtained 194 distinct lemmas and quantified their importance in each report. We then applied principal components analysis to obtain 18 underlying behavioral factors. Finally, we clustered the reports via Gaussian Mixture Modeling, obtaining a novel typology of 15 behaviors. Our results reveal spatial disparities in fatal driver behaviors and provide a framework for type-specific crash mitigation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benefits of aggressively co-undergrounding electric and broadband lines outweigh costs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-benefits-aggressively-coundergrounding/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-arabi-benefits-aggressively-coundergrounding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Electric power and broadband have become essential services for modern economies, but utilities face substantial challenges in providing disruption-free access. Recent legislation, including the US Infrastructure Investment and Jobs Act of 2021, has allocated enormous resources toward improving infrastructure systems. Historically, undergrounding has enhanced system reliability but has been cost effective only in densely populated areas. We investigate the conditions under which undergrounding becomes cost effective, particularly when co-deployed with fiber optic lines. We introduce a novel data-driven cost-benefit model and conduct a detailed localized case study in Shrewsbury, Massachusetts. The results indicate that when undergrounding is viable, aggressively co-undergrounding yields the highest net benefit. This finding is robust across various assumptions. Importantly, our model highlights the importance of assumptions regarding undergrounding’s effectiveness in reducing outages. Our model is readily deployable to other study areas, providing effective decision-making capabilities even with limited data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Vision for Computational Decarbonization of Societal Infrastructure</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-irwin-vision-computational-decarbonization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2025-irwin-vision-computational-decarbonization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Modern society is at a critical inflection point with rapidly accelerating demand for energy due to growth in domestic manufacturing, datacenters, artificial intelligence (AI), electric vehicles, and electric heat pumps. Sustaining this growth while also reducing society’s carbon emissions will necessitate a shift beyond our long-standing focus on improving energy efficiency to optimizing carbon efficiency. This paper lays out a vision for a new field of computational decarbonization, which focuses on optimizing and reducing the lifecycle carbon emissions of complex computing and societal infrastructure systems. We identify an important class of decarbonization problems that arise from interdependencies across multiple infrastructure domains, including computing, transportation, the built environment, and the electric power grid. As we discuss, solving these problems will require developing novel computational techniques, algorithms, systems, and AI methods that sense, optimize, and reduce the operational, embodied, and lifecycle greenhouse gas emissions of societal infrastructure over long temporal and spatial scales.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Seasonal Typology-Informed Transit Trip Chaining via Mobile Boarding and Survey Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-abdalazeem-enhanced-seasonal-typologyinformed/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-abdalazeem-enhanced-seasonal-typologyinformed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trip chaining is essential in estimating transit demand models based on big data sources, which hold advantages over traditional data collection methods in terms of both accuracy and cost-effectiveness. However, regional transit systems, accounting for 60% of transit systems in the United States, are often not equipped with smart card systems that are typically needed for trip chaining due to the high costs involved. This study introduces an innovative trip chaining framework that leverages boarding-only mobile ticketing automated fare collection (AFC) data. Our approach incorporates spatiotemporal passenger types obtained via typology analysis. This is followed by calibrating type-specific and season-aware parameters using survey data supplied by the network operators. We then trained a gradient boosting machine to learn the error structure of the initial trip chaining flow estimates and augment final trip frequency predictions. Our findings demonstrate that incorporating spatial error correction significantly improves the trip chaining results. However, the best performance is achieved when season-awareness and typology information are integrated with spatial error correction, reducing the mean absolute error (MAE) by approximately 70% and the symmetric mean absolute percentage error (SMAPE) by 85%. Furthermore, the typology, which we validate with a classification model, provides a deeper understanding of passenger travel characteristics which can facilitate further planning efforts. The spatial error correction model also provides insights into portions of the network that can be better targeted for survey data collection and mobile ticketing adoption to improve future models. Overall, this research will enable regional transit planners to efficiently utilize limited resources and generate valuable insights that would otherwise remain inaccessible.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Decision-Making Framework for Sustainable Operations and Planning of MBTA Rapid Transit Vehicles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-han-robust-decisionmaking-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-han-robust-decisionmaking-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban Rail Transit (URT) systems play a critical role in modern cities but consume significant amounts of energy. Understanding and predicting energy consumption patterns in these systems is vital for sustainable urban planning, especially during disruptive events. This study presents a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) recurrent neural network, the model can accurately predict daily energy consumption and average daily temperature, with root mean squared errors (RMSE) of 50.6 MWh and 6.62°F. Additionally, a decision-making tool was developed to simulate various operational strategies and their impacts on energy consumption and temperature. These findings provide URT operators with a robust framework for making data-driven decisions and improving energy efficiency in URT systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feature Engineering and Decision Trees for Predicting High Crash-Risk Locations Using Roadway Indicators</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-sarigiannis-feature-engineering-decision/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-sarigiannis-feature-engineering-decision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Road crashes are a prevalent public health issue across the globe. The objective of this research was to develop a methodology for accurately classifying high-risk crash locations. The hypothesis of this study was that readily obtained roadway indicators can be used along with machine learning techniques to categorize locations as high crash-risk. A database containing 5,383 locations was created during 2012 to 2015 as part of the Hellenic National Road Safety Project and used to develop three binary machine learning models to classify high crash-risk locations based on roadway indicators. The three models were random forest, gradient boosting, and extra trees. This research used features engineering to reduce the number of indicators in the model, and the synthetic minority oversampling technique to address imbalances in the dataset between the minority (high crash-risk locations identified using crash reports) and majority classes (medium to low crash-risk locations identified based on local police testimonies, site inspections, and geometry analysis). Although all three models performed similarly, the extra trees model outperformed the other two on a range of performance metrics, including the area under the precision–recall curve and the F1-score. The findings revealed that design speeds, pavement markings, signage presence, and pavement condition were the most influential factors affecting roadway safety. The contribution of this research is in the development of a transferable methodology for classifying high crash-risk locations in addition to revealing key indicators for crash-risk potential, which in turn can inform cost-effective data collection and maintenance activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resilience in multilayer transportation infrastructure networks: a review and conceptual framework for equity-based assessment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-arabi-resilience-multilayer-transportation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-arabi-resilience-multilayer-transportation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a comprehensive review of resilience concepts, methodologies, metrics, and modeling techniques, and identifies key research gaps. These include the lack of multilayer network representations of transportation infrastructures when quantifying resilience, and insufficient metrics for assessing equitable outcomes. To address these gaps, we propose a conceptual multilayer framework for transporttaion infrastructure networks and develop equitable resilience metrics that incorporate socioeconomic and demographic variables. Using Pioneer Valley as a case study, we apply our framework to assess the resilience of transportation networks and demonstrate its utility in guiding resource allocation to enhance both the physical robustness and social equity of infrastructure. Our findings show that this approach significantly contributes to more informed and inclusive decision-making, fostering the development of resilient and equitable urban environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence Framework for Crosswalk Detection Across Massachusetts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-apostolov-artificial-intelligence-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-apostolov-artificial-intelligence-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to develop an artificial intelligence (AI) framework to detect crosswalk locations across the state of Massachusetts, as well as their type classification (continental, parallel lines, or solid) and location category (intersection, midblock, or driveway). Aerial images downloaded from MassGIS were annotated, and these were used to train the AI model, which was then used to detect crosswalks across the entire state using images from both 2019 and 2021. About 88,000 crosswalks were detected in 2021. In terms of location category, 89% of these were intersection crosswalks, 8% were midblock, and 3% were at driveways. In terms of type, just under 65% were continental (zebra-style) crosswalks, about 35% were parallel lines, and less than 1% were solid/painted crosswalks. A python script was developed to perform the post-processing. The model and the post-processing script will be available to MassDOT to perform further analyses, and results will be expected to inform maintenance and safety initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive Energy Modeling Framework for Multi-Powertrain Bus Transit Systems</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-arabi-comprehensive-energy-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-arabi-comprehensive-energy-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the increasing emphasis on sustainable transportation solutions, there is an urgent need for a system that can accurately assess vehicle-specific energy consumption in real-time. However, the current modeling frameworks have a significant gap in that they are not demand- and congestion-responsive, nor are they capable of modeling the system-wide energy consumption of bus fleets at the vehicle-level, encompassing all three types of powertrains—conventional, hybrid, and electric. To address this gap, we present a comprehensive modeling framework that takes into account passenger loading, considers the dynamics of the system including acceleration, and is capable of predicting the real-time energy usage of each bus in a transit network. Using the Pioneer Valley Transit Authority system as a case study, we calibrated existing powertrain-specific models for conventional diesel, hybrid, and battery electric buses. Our demand- and congestion-responsive energy consumption modeling framework fills this critical gap and offers significant potential for future sustainable transportation planning. Relying on detailed trajectories computed from one month of bus location data, along with passenger counts and road grade, our framework is a novel contribution in that it provides spatiotemporal energy predictions for an entire bus system. As it is readily calibrated with potential improvements in accuracy given more data, this framework can be applied by transit agencies for the purposes of real-time energy consumption monitoring, fleet electrification planning, equity analyses, and carbon emission reduction strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line-Specific Energy Modeling Framework for Urban Rail Transit Systems: A Case Study of Boston</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-han-linespecific-energy-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2024-han-linespecific-energy-modeling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban rail transit systems play an essential role in improving mobility and efficiency. A complex rail transit network serves the Boston metropolitan area, U.S., which costs $38 million for the 422 GWh of system electricity consumed annually. With the aim of developing a tool for energy and cost reduction decision support, we propose a comprehensive machine learning framework to investigate line-specific contributions to energy. This effort builds on prior work in estimating a system-wide energy model for the Boston network. By introducing line-specific train movement and operation variables, we obtain a higher-performing model  (R2=0.91) . Furthermore, the model better explains the relationship between energy and train movement, ridership, and weather variables. Most importantly, the model facilitates analyses of how each line contributes to system consumption at the hour level. We found that the non-line-specific variables made a contribution of −2.7% to the average hourly energy of consumption of −5.4 MWh with a baseline energy consumption of 39 MWh. The Red Line dominates the energy consumption among line-specific variables, contributing 2.3% to the hourly average. Our model could be further enhanced to evaluate the energy and cost impacts of line-specific strategies that may be required for future planning and disaster response, as well as for real-time energy monitoring by line.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting tree failure likelihood for utility risk mitigation via a convolutional neural network</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-apostolov-predicting-tree-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-apostolov-predicting-tree-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Critical to the resilience of utility power lines, tree failure assessments have historically been performed via costly manual inspections. In this paper, we develop a convolutional neural network (CNN) to predict tree failure likelihood categories (Probable, Possible, Improbable) under three classification strategies. The CNN produced the best performance under the Probable/Possible vs. Improbable strategy, achieving a recall score of 0.82. We also perform a visual analysis of the predictions via Grad-CAM++ heatmaps, indicating an approach for incorporating interpretability into model selection. Benchmarking the results of our model against those produced by two state-of-the-art CNNs (ResNet-50 and Inception-v3), we show that our relatively simple model produces better results in a computational time that is three times faster. Via this novel framework, we demonstrate the potential of artificial intelligence to automate and consequently reduce the costs of tree failure likelihood assessments in proximity to power lines, thereby promoting sustainable infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Spatiotemporal Bus Passenger Trip Typologies from Noisy Mobile Ticketing Boarding Data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-abdalazeem-extracting-spatiotemporal-bus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-abdalazeem-extracting-spatiotemporal-bus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a framework for extracting spatiotemporal trip typologies using noisy mobile ticketing boarding data sampled from passengers in a bus network. Our case study was the Pioneer Valley Transit Authority in Massachusetts. We first used a greedy approach to infer bus boarding stops. Next, we calculated the multi-dimensional dissimilarity of passenger activation time series using the AWarp alignment algorithm for sparse time series. We then employed hierarchical clustering to discover the spatiotemporal patterns, resulting in four distinct trip pattern typologies. We analyzed the typologies, based on trip length and duration, seasonality and other temporal distributions, spatial distributions, and faretype. Three typologies were linked to regular commuters, distinguished by boarding time or transfer tendency. The fourth typology was primarily associated with leisure or other activities. Our typology method provides valuable passenger behavioral insights and can facilitate demand estimation by planners. Further, we demonstrate a potential for decision-making support for other regional transit authorities with limited passenger data availability.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic analysis for estimating track geometry degradation rates based on GPR and LiDAR data</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-goodarzi-stochastic-analysis-estimating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-goodarzi-stochastic-analysis-estimating/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The estimation of track degradation rate is a challenging step in scheduling preventive maintenance interventions due to its uncertain nature. To tackle this challenge, a large dataset of historic passenger track geometry data, between 2011 and 2021, integrated with Ground Penetrating Radar (GPR), and Light Detection And Ranging (LiDAR) data are investigated. Stochastic models are proposed for estimating the expected track degradation rates based on subsurface and drainage conditions of blocks and also a framework is proposed for automatically evaluating drainage conditions of track from LiDAR data. Results indicate that the probability of having high track degradation rates in highly fouled ballast condition can be 10 times more than in clean ballast condition. In addition, analyzing the effect of drainage conditions revealed that sections with poor drainage conditions are 30% more likely to have high track degradation rates than sections with moderate drainage conditions. The results of this study enhance scheduling geometry maintenance and provide reliable information for decision making on different types of maintenance such as Ballast Cleaning and ditching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin-destination inference in public transportation systems: A comprehensive review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-mohammed-origindestination-inference-public/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-mohammed-origindestination-inference-public/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Origin-destination (OD) modeling facilitates effective demand-responsive public transportation planning in order to meet emergent needs. Given recent advances in transit information and personal communications technology, transit OD estimation methods have evolved from relying on limited survey sources to automated big data sources. Innovative modeling approaches have also been developed over several decades to estimate trip ODs, not only for single routes, but also for full networks, including transfers. In this paper, we synthesize a review of the state of the art in research and practice, along with descriptions of key data types and methodological approaches, indicating how they interact. We also discuss current research gaps and opportunities for further innovation. This review provides a comprehensive resource that should facilitate the application of these methods to various transit systems, thus enabling planners and policymakers to gain insights from new and improved model estimates in various transit systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drinking water accessibility typologies in low- and middle-income countries</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-chung-drinking-water-accessibility/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2023-chung-drinking-water-accessibility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a data-driven typology framework for understanding patterns in drinking water accessibility across low- and middle-income countries. Further, we obtain novel typology-specific insights regarding the relationships between possible explanatory variables and typology outcomes. First, we conducted exploratory factor analysis to obtain a smaller set of interpretable factors from the initial set of 17 drinking water accessibility indicators from 73 countries. The resulting seven factors summarize the key drivers for water accessibility, and also serve as a vehicle for framing discussions on country outcomes. We clustered the countries based on their seven-dimensional water accessibility factor scores, referring to the resulting three clusters as ‘typologies,’ namely, Decentralized, Centralized and Hybrid. The typologies serve as a vehicle for analyzing water accessibility among countries with similar patterns, in contrast with geographically-based approaches. Finally, we fitted a decision tree classifier to analyze relationships between a country’s typology membership and socioeconomic, geographic and transportation explanatory variables. We found that private car ownership, population density and per-capita gross domestic product are most relevant in predicting a country’s drinking water accessibility typology.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling System-Wide Urban Rail Transit Energy Consumption: A Case Study of Boston</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2022-han-modeling-systemwide-urban/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2022-han-modeling-systemwide-urban/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rapid transit systems are critical components of urban public transportation networks in their impact, not only on personal mobility but also on the energy and environmental costs associated with network operations. To facilitate effective planning for current and future needs, a framework is required that provides important consumption metrics and also explains the various contributors to energy consumption, along with their interactions. To address this gap, we estimated models that utilized operational and ridership data for the Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority?s rapid transit system, as well as ambient temperature, to accurately predict system-wide electricity consumption. The models were trained with data from 2019 and tested with data from 2020. The estimated multiple linear regression (MLR) and random forest (RF) models explained 93% and 95% of the variance in the data set, respectively. The MLR model provided predictions with a root mean squared error (RMSE) of 2.7?MWh and mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) of 4.68%, while the RF model resulted in an RMSE of 2.94?MWh and MAPE of 5.01%. We also investigated the impacts of COVID-19 on the transit system by exploring the effects on ridership, energy consumption, cost, and train movement metrics before and during the pandemic. We find that the models are robust and perform well, even with the significant disruptions associated with the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven methods to predict track degradation: A case study</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2022-goodarzi-datadriven-methods-predict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2022-goodarzi-datadriven-methods-predict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Predicting track degradation is extremely important due to its beneficial effects on increasing track safety and scheduling preventive maintenance. Logistic regression and Gradient Boosting Machine (GBM) were employed in this paper for predicting Yellow-tag Defect in the Next Inspection (YDNI), which is an indicator of maintenance requirement in the track. The geometry data of this paper were collected from passenger tracks with a length of 155 miles from 2011 to 2020. In addition to geometry data, Ground Penetrating Radar (GPR) data were used as additional explanatory variables to improve the performance of models. As there are a limited number of YDNI observations, Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique (SMOTE) is employed to resolve the issue of imbalance dataset. Results indicate that the GBM outperforms logistic regression and can successfully predict YDNI with a very high sensitivity of 0.94. Parametric analysis indicated the direct correlation between the Ballast Fouling Index (BFI) and the probability of defect occurrence. Finally, the model can be integrated into a decision-making framework which generates predictions based on a given probability threshold for classification. Thus, the railway companies can select a specific threshold according to their maintenance budget and desired level of track safety for scheduling preventive maintenance interventions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Who benefits from AVs? Equity implications of automated vehicles policies in full-scale prototype cities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-nahmias-biran-benefits-avs-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-nahmias-biran-benefits-avs-equity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While researchers have stressed the potential of automated vehicle (AV) technology in improving mobility and accessibility for a range of people, only a few attempts have been made to examine the impact of this new technology on different segments of the population in a realistic setting using high-fidelity simulation. To fill this gap, we analyze the equity implications of Automated Mobility-on-Demand (AMoD) in three full-scale prototype cities using SimMobility, a state-of-the-art activity- and agent-based framework. The prototype cities were developed based on two auto-dependent typologies, representing cities largely in the US/Canada, and a dense transit-oriented typology. We perform equity analyses at the individual and income-group level, in order to reveal the winners and losers from the introduction of AVs under two scenarios: (1) AMoD Intro, in which a low-cost AMoD service competes with mass transit, and (2) AMoD Transit Integration, where AMoD complements mass transit, via access/egress connectivity service to rapid transit stations. We evaluate the following outcomes: induced demand by age and income groups, mode share by income levels, individual kilometers traveled by different modes and income levels, and the spatial distribution of change in fare and accessibility. Outcomes are considered as equity-oriented if they reduce accessibility gaps, particularly among disadvantaged populations. Our results indicate that in large population-dense and transit-oriented cities, the most equity-oriented outcomes can be achieved, due to extensive mass transit usage, which depresses car usage and restricts induced demand for AMoD. Such cities provide greater opportunities for low-income groups. Specifically, the AMoD Transit Integration scenario results in the best outcomes and implies a new market share, as disadvantaged groups, such as children and low-income individuals, were able to travel more using the integrated AMoD-transit service. Nevertheless, in car-dependent cities, where accessibility gaps are much larger, AMoD Intro scenario performs better compared to AMoD Transit Integration, as it serves the less accessible population and significantly improves their opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Activity-based epidemic propagation and contact network scaling in auto-dependent metropolitan areas</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-kumar-activitybased-epidemic-propagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-kumar-activitybased-epidemic-propagation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We build on recent work to develop a fully mechanistic, activity-based and highly spatio-temporally resolved epidemiological model which leverages person-trajectories obtained from an activity-based model calibrated for two full-scale prototype cities, consisting of representative synthetic populations and mobility networks for two contrasting auto-dependent city typologies. We simulate the propagation of the COVID-19 epidemic in both cities to analyze spreading patterns in urban networks across various activity types. Investigating the impact of the transit network, we find that its removal dampens disease propagation significantly, suggesting that transit restriction is more critical for mitigating post-peak disease spreading in transit dense cities. In the latter stages of disease spread, we find that the greatest share of infections occur at work locations. A statistical analysis of the resulting activity-based contact networks indicates that transit contacts are scale-free, work contacts are Weibull distributed, and shopping or leisure contacts are exponentially distributed. We validate our simulation results against existing case and mortality data across multiple cities in their respective typologies. Our framework demonstrates the potential for tracking epidemic propagation in urban networks, analyzing socio-demographic impacts and assessing activity- and mobility-specific implications of both non-pharmaceutical and pharmaceutical intervention strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the impacts of shared automated mobility on-demand services: an activity-based accessibility approach</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-nahmias-biran-evaluating-impacts-shared/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-nahmias-biran-evaluating-impacts-shared/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Autonomous vehicle (AV) technologies are under constant improvement with pilot programs now underway in several urban areas worldwide. Modeling and field-testing efforts are demonstrating that shared mobility coupled with AV technology for automated mobility on-demand (AMoD) service may significantly impact levels of service and environmental outcomes in future cities. Given these rapidly emerging developments, there is an urgent need for methods to adequately quantify the economic impacts of new vehicle technologies and future urban mobility policy. In this paper, we show how broader user-centric impacts can be captured by the activity-based accessibility (ABA) measure, which takes advantage of the rich data and outcomes of utility-maximization activity-based models and its interaction with mesoscale agent-based traffic simulation frameworks. Using the SimMobility simulator, we evaluate shared AMoD strategies applied to a Singapore micromodel city testbed. A near-future strategy of exclusive availability of AMoD service in the central business district (CBD), and a further-horizon strategy of the full operation of AMoD city-wide in the absence of other on-demand services, were tested and evaluated. Our results provide insights into the income and accessibility effects on the population under the implementation of shared and automated mobility policies. The outcomes indicate that the city-wide deployment of AMoD results in greater accessibility and network performance. Moreover, the accessibility of low-income individuals is improved relative to that of mid- and high-income individuals. The restriction of AMoD to the CBD along with the operation of other on-demand services, however, provides a certain level of disbenefit to segments of the population in two exceptional cases. The first is to high-income individuals who live in a suburban zone and rely heavily on on-demand services; the second is to mid-income residents that have excellent public transportation coverage with close proximity to the CBD. We further establish the efficacy of the ABA measure, as these findings motivate the need for measuring socioeconomic impacts at the individual level. The work presented here serves as a foundation for policy evaluation in real-world urban models for future mobility paradigms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking the Energy and Emissions of MBTA Rapid Transit Vehicles</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-oke-tracking-energy-emissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2021-oke-tracking-energy-emissions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rapid transit systems are critical components of public transportation networks in urban areas, in terms of their impact on person mobility and on monetary, energy, and environmental costs associated with their operations. To facilitate effective planning for current and future needs, a framework is required that provides important consumption metrics and explains the various contributors to energy consumption and their interactions. This study presents a model that utilizes operational and ridership data for the Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority&amp;rsquo;s rapid transit system, as well as ambient temperature, to accurately predict system-wide electricity consumption. Linear regression and random forests were used to estimate energy consumption, which could explain a 0.93 and 0.95 variance in the data set, respectively. The model was trained with data from 2019 and tested with data from 2020. The linear regression model provided predictions with RMSE of 2.7 MWh and MAPE of 4.68%, and the random forest model resulted in a RMSE of 2.94 MWh and MAPE of 5.01%. These models are robust and perform well, even with the significant impacts to transit operations associated with the COVID-19 pandemic. This project also investigated COVID-19 impact on the whole system by exploring effects on ridership, energy consumption, cost, and train movement metrics, before and during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the systemic effects of automated mobility-on-demand services via large-scale agent-based simulation of auto-dependent prototype cities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2020-oke-evaluating-systemic-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2020-oke-evaluating-systemic-effects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The growing demand for urban mobility highlights the need for relevant and sustainable solutions in cities worldwide. Thus, we develop and implement a framework to analyze the systemic impacts of future urban mobility trends and policies. We build on prior work in classifying the world’s cities into 12 urban typologies that represent distinct land-use and behavioral characteristics by introducing a generalized approach for creating a detailed, simulatable prototype city that is representative of a given typology. We then generate and simulate two auto-dependent (largely US-specific) prototype cities via a state-of-the-art agent-based platform, SimMobility, for integrated demand microsimulation and supply mesoscopic simulation. We demonstrate the framework by analyzing the impacts of automated mobility on-demand (AMoD) implementation strategies in the cities based on demand, congestion, energy consumption and emissions outcomes. Our results show that the introduction of AMoD cannibalizes mass transit while increasing vehicle kilometers traveled (VKT) and congestion. In sprawling auto-dependent cities with low transit penetration, the congestion and energy consumption effects under best-case assumptions are similar regardless of whether AMoD competes with or complements mass transit. In dense auto-dependent cities with moderate transit modeshare, the integration of AMoD with transit yields better outcomes in terms of VKT and congestion. Such cities cannot afford to disinvest in mass transit, as this would result in unsustainable outcomes. Overall, this framework can provide insights into how AMoD can be sustainably harnessed not only in low-density and high-density auto-dependent cities, but also in other typologies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where is my infusion pump? Harnessing network dynamics for improved hospital equipment fleet management</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2020-martinez-infusion-pump-harnessing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2020-martinez-infusion-pump-harnessing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AbstractObjective.  Timely availability of intravenous infusion pumps is critical for high-quality care delivery. Pumps are shared among hospital units, often w&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Traditional to Automated Mobility on Demand: A Comprehensive Framework for Modeling On-Demand Services in SimMobility</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-nahmias-biran-traditional-automated-mobility/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-nahmias-biran-traditional-automated-mobility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mobility on demand (MoD) systems have recently emerged as a promising paradigm for sustainable personal urban mobility in cities. In the context of multi-agent simulation technology, the state-of-the-art lacks a platform that captures the dynamics between decentralized driver decision-making and the centralized coordinated decision-making. This work aims to fill this gap by introducing a comprehensive framework that models various facets of MoD, namely heterogeneous MoD driver decision-making and coordinated fleet management within SimMobility, an agent- and activity-based demand model integrated with a dynamic multi-modal network assignment model. To facilitate such a study, we propose an event-based modeling framework. Behavioral models were estimated to characterize the decision-making of drivers using a GPS dataset from a major MoD fleet operator in Singapore. The proposed framework was designed to accommodate behaviors of multiple on-demand services such as traditional MoD, Lyft-like services, and automated MoD (AMoD) services which interact with traffic simulators and a multi-modal transportation network. We demonstrate the benefits of the proposed framework through a large-scale case study in Singapore comparing the fully decentralized traditional MoD with the future AMoD services in a realistic simulation setting. We found that AMoD results in a more efficient service even with increased demand. Parking strategies and fleet sizes will also have an effect on user satisfaction and network performance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights Into Future Mobility: A Report from the Mobility of the Future Study</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-green-insights-into-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-green-insights-into-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The MIT Energy Initiative&amp;rsquo;s (MITEI&amp;rsquo;s) three-year Mobility of the Future study explored the major factors that affect the evolution of personal mobility from 2020 to 2050. Using a scenario-based approach, the diverse study team of MIT faculty, researchers, and students examined how different factors shape the future of personal mobility at different scales, from global and national markets to policy and mobility choices at the city and individual levels. This report presents results and findings to help stakeholders anticipate and navigate the challenges that lie ahead. The report includes detailed findings on five areas of influence on the future landscape for personal mobility: (1) The potential impact of climate change policies on global fleet composition, fuel consumption, fuel prices, and economic output; (2) The outlook for vehicle ownership and travel, with a focus on the world’s two largest light-duty vehicle markets—the U.S. and China; (3) Characteristics of alternative vehicle powertrains and fuels that could affect their future market share; (4) Infrastructure considerations for charging and fueling, particularly as they affect future demand for electric and hydrogen fuel cell vehicles; and (5) The future of personal mobility in urban areas, with a focus on the potentially disruptive role of autonomous vehicles and ride-hailing services.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel global urban typology framework for sustainable mobility futures</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-oke-novel-global-urban/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-oke-novel-global-urban/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Urban mobility significantly contributes to global carbon dioxide emissions. Given the rapid expansion and growth in urban areas, cities thus require innovative policies to ensure efficient and sustainable mobility. Urban typologies can serve as a vehicle for understanding dynamics of cities, which exhibit high variability in form, economic output, mobility behavior, among others. Yet, typologies relevant for sustainable urban mobility analyses are few, outdated and not large enough in scope. In this paper, we present a new typologization spanning 331 cities in 124 countries. Our sample represents 40% of the global urban population and contains the most recent data from 2008 to date. Using a factor analytic and agglomerative clustering approach, we identify 9 urban factors and 12 typologies. We discuss the implications of this new framework for researchers and planners and investigate the relationships between mobility and environmental sustainability indicators. Notably, we show an immediate application of the urban typologies to better understanding travel behavior and also describe their usage for detailed large-scale simulation in representative prototype cities for insights into sustainable future mobility policy pathways. Our data and results are publicly available for further exploration and will serve as a foundation for future analyses toward desirable urban and environmental outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Transportation Flows in Energy Networks with an Application to Crude Oil Markets</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-oke-multimodal-transportation-flows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2019-oke-multimodal-transportation-flows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Network models of energy markets have been beneficial for analyses and decision-making to tackle challenges related to the production, distribution and consumption of energy in its various forms. Despite the growing awareness of environmental and safety impacts of fuel transfer, such as emissions, spills and other harmful effects, existing energy models for various types of networks are yet to fully capture modal distinctions which are relevant to providing pathways to limiting these impacts. To address this deficit in detailed multimodal analyses, we have built on recent work to develop a partial-equilibrium model that incorporates the representation of multimodal fuel transfer within energy networks. In a novel application to the North American crude oil market, we also demonstrate that our model is a useful tool for exploring avenues for reducing the risks of light and heavy crude oil transportation across this region. The results we obtain indicate that a combined strategy of rail loading restrictions, pipeline deployments and a discontinuation of the oil export ban is most effective in reducing the transportation of crude oil by rail and thereby mitigating the associated risks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial associations in global household bicycle ownership</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2018-oke-spatial-associations-global/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2018-oke-spatial-associations-global/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The interest in bicycling and its determining factors is growing within the public health, transportation and geography communities. Ownership is one factor affecting bicycle usage, but work is still ongoing to not only quantify its effects but also to understand patterns in its growth and influence. In recent work, we mined and discovered patterns in global bicycle ownership that showed the existence of four characteristic country groups and their trends. Building on these results, we show in this paper that the ownership dataset can be modeled as a network. First, we observe mixing tendencies that indicate neighboring countries are more likely to be in the same ownership group and we map the likelihoods for cross-group mixings. Further, we define the strength of connections between countries by their proximity in ownership levels. We then determine the weighted degree assortative coefficient for the network and for each group relative to the network. We find that while the weighted degree assortativity of the ownership network is statistically insignificant, the highest and lowest ownership groups exhibit disassortative behavior with respect to the entire network. The second and third ranked groups, however, are strongly assortative. Our model serves as a step toward further work in studying the relationship between proximity and bicycle ownership among nations and unearthing possible patterns of influence. Considering further developments, this work can inform policy-relevant recommendations toward regional planning. This effort also contributes to expanding research in assortativity analyses, especially in weighted networks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking global bicycle ownership patterns</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2015-oke-tracking-global-bicycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2015-oke-tracking-global-bicycle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past four decades, bicycle ownership has been documented in various countries but not globally analyzed. This paper presents an effort to fill this gap by tracking household bicycle possession. First, we gather survey data from 150 countries and extract percentage household bicycle ownership values. Performing cluster analysis, we determined four groups with the weighted mean percentage ownership ranging from 20% to 81%. Generally, bicycle ownership was highest in Northern Europe and lowest in West, Central and North Africa, and Central Asia. We determine worldwide household ownership patterns and demonstrate a basis for understanding the global impact of cycling as a sustainable transit mode. Furthermore, we find a lower-bound estimate of the number of bicycles available to the world׳s households. We establish that at the global level 42% of households own at least one bicycle, and thus there are at least 580 million bicycles in private household ownership. Our data are publicly available and amenable for future analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient automated schematic map drawing using multiobjective mixed integer programming</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2015-oke-efficient-automated-schematic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2015-oke-efficient-automated-schematic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present an efficient multiobjective mixed binary linear program that automates schematic mapping for network visualization and navigation. Schematic mapping has broad applications in representing transit networks, circuits, disease pathways, project tasks, organograms, and taxonomies. Good schematic maps employ distortion while preserving topology to facilitate access to physical or virtual networks. Automation is critical to saving time and costs, while encouraging adoption. We build upon previous work, particularly that of Nöllenburg and Wolff, improving upon the computational efficiency of their model by relaxing integrality constraints and reducing the number of objectives from three to two. We also employ an efficient augmented ϵ-constraint method to assist in obtaining all Pareto optimal solutions, both supported and unsupported, for a given network. Through the Vienna Underground network and a cancer pathway, along with three numerical examples, we demonstrate the applications of our methods. Finally, we discuss future directions for research in this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement and Composite Bosons</title>
      <link>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2010-chudzicki-entanglement-composite-bosons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:36719/jimi/publications/2010-chudzicki-entanglement-composite-bosons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We build upon work by C. K. Law [Phys. Rev. A 71, 034306 (2005)] to show in general that the entanglement between two fermions largely determines the extent to which the pair behaves like an elementary boson. Specifically, we derive upper and lower bounds on a quantity χN+1/χN that governs the bosonic character of a pair of fermions when N such pairs approximately share the same wave function. Our bounds depend on the purity of the single-particle density matrix, an indicator of entanglement, and demonstrate that if the entanglement is sufficiently strong, the quantity χN+1/χN approaches its ideal bosonic value.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
